I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
Distant Thunder (Part 2)
（幸田(こうだ)香子(きょうこ)）気が重いでしょ？
Isn't that a downer?
It's like you're going over there to strangle an old, senile dog.
老いた犬の首を
絞めに行くようなものだものね
It kind of makes you worry.
な〜んか 心配なのよね
I thought that in a situation like this,
maybe you're the type to throw the match.
あなたって こういうとき
わざと負けてあげたり
しちゃうんじゃないかとか—
思っちゃって
Seeing as you're such a nice guy.
だってほら あなたって優しいから
Matsunaga Shouichi.
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）
松永正一(まつながしょういち) ７段 65歳
7-dan.
Sixty-five years old.
From Fukushima Prefecture.
福島県出身
He turned pro at 25.
25歳でプロ棋士になる
He has forty years of experience.
棋士歴40年
最高成績 Ｂ１に１期
At his best, he was in Class B1 for a season.
I've spotted him many times at the shogi hall.
会館で 何度か
姿を見かけたことがある
小柄で しゃきしゃき歩く
後ろ姿をしていた
I saw the back of a short-statured man who always walked briskly.
Sendagaya Station
Seeing this same scenery for forty years...
この風景を40年…
"Forty years."
40年…
I said it out loud, but I couldn't imagine it.
口に出してみたけれど
まるで想像がつかなかった
That's over twice as long as I've been alive.
僕の人生の倍以上の年月
On this 81-square board, he's lived and died over and over.
この81マスの盤の上で
生き死にを繰り返した人
（零）松永さん
Matsunaga...
（香子）松永さん
Ｃ２に降級したら引退ですって
I hear if Matsunaga is demoted to C2, he'll finally retire.
（零）40年
Forty years...
A mind-boggling span of time.
気が遠くなるほどの年月
I wonder how he feels right now.
今 どんな気持ちなんだろう
僕には想像もつかないけれど…
I can't imagine.
Well, crap.
（松永）まいったなぁ
ハア
To be honest, God, I just want to go home.
（松永）神様　もう正直
帰っちゃいたいような気持ちです
あっ でも お願いですから
どうか勝たしてください
But please let me win somehow!
Clap, clap. And so on.
パン パンっとね
What?!
（零）そんな気持ち？
That's how he feels?!
Shock
True, I didn't imagine that.
確かに 想像もつかなかったよ
Now he's drawing a fortune paper!
そして おみくじ引いてるよ！
And he's incredibly agitated!
しかも
ものすごい動揺してるし
What did it say?!
（零）
でもって 何が書いてあったの？
めっちゃ落ち込んでるんですけど
Oh no, he looks super depressed!
ていうか 引かないで おみくじ
こんなときに
Actually, why would you draw a fortune at a time like this?!
い… 行こう
I-I should go! I need to get to the table, calm down, and wait for him.
早く席に着いて 落ち着いて待とう
Feels like he saw something
he shouldn't have
Shogi Hall
So... um...
（零）で あの…
Matsunaga isn't here!
来ないんですけど 松永さん
Thump
D-Don't tell me he really went...
まさか 本当に帰っ…
Thump
He's here!
来た　よかった
What a relief.
He stopped?
止まった？
He's not moving?
動かな… い？
H-He moved.
う… 動いた
Is this psychological warfare?
心理戦？
Or some kind of veteran player strategy?
これがベテランの
何らかの作戦なのか？
It's time.
（記録係）時間になりました
よろしくお願いします
Please begin.
（零）お願いします
If you would.
So, how will he play?
さあ どう来るか
Sharp
Forty years...
（零）40年…
What will my life be like in forty years?
40年後の僕は
どんなふうに生きてるのかな
S-5c? Is he doing the Bear in the Castle?
５三銀　穴熊か？
He surrounds himself, and then tries to have a long, careful battle?
堅く囲って
長期戦でじっくりということか
Then I'll go with P-1e.
じゃあ こっちは１五歩
玉は動かさず
いつでも攻めに出られる形に
That keeps the king pinned down
so I can attack whenever I need to.
P-7d. A sudden attack?
７四歩　急戦？
He's not doing Bear in the Castle?
穴熊ではないのか
（熊）プイ
Hmph!
I can't tell what his strategy is.
読めないな 作戦が
Then I'll respond with...
じゃあ こっちは…
L-1b?
１二香？
What? So he's doing Bear in the Castle after all?
Upsy daisy.
えっ 何？ やっぱり穴熊なの？
Continue operation
I can't tell what he's doing.
読めない　何だ？ これ
Moving the pieces randomly?
行き当たりばったりなわけないよね
No, there's no way.
I think he's just trying to confuse me.
多分 かく乱だよね
He has some kind of plan, right?
きっと 何か策があるんだよね？
The calm mind
is the way
White
Matsunaga, 7-Dan
（熊）よじ よじ　フ〜
Shuffle, shuffle. Phew.
The bear goes in!
All right, it's in there.
（零）よし　入ったな
Here I go!
じゃあ 行きます
７五歩
P-7e.
（零）ボーッ？
ん？ 今 変な音が…
Did he just make a weird noise?
ヒュ〜
（松永）うう…
（零）何て顔
What expression is that?!
The bishop... Um... knight...
角が… えっと…　うっく…
ん？ へっ？
序盤 考えてなかったの？
What?!
Pawn...
Wait a minute, he wasn't thinking about it?!
No countermeasure against P-7e?!
７五歩対策
後ろに誰か見えるし…
And I can see someone behind him!
Bam!
（記録係）おっと…
Whoa...
So S-3b?!
（零）で ３二銀？
Now he's doing Mino Castle?!
今度は美濃(みの)囲いに？
Thump
Then I'll do N-7g.
（零）じゃあ ７七桂(けい)で
Wait, it's coming out?!
Matsunaga, 7-Dan
...K-2b
（零）えっ？ 出てきちゃったよ！
いなよ そこ
今動いたら 熊さん危ないってば！
Please stay there! If you move now, you'll be in trouble, Mr. Bear!
Eeeek!
ハア〜
Th-This is painful.
（零）つ… 辛い
何だか とっても辛いんですけど
For some reason, it's very painful.
おっ　し… しまった
Shoot.
Yikes. The king and rook are in check.
あちゃ〜 王手飛車じゃ
Huh?
確かに
でも そこに角を打ったら
That's true.
But if I place the bishop there,
he'll do B*5e, and then do N*3f...
５五に角を合わされて
３六桂で
まあ 怪しくはなっても
Well, that's dubious...
それでも
僕の方が優勢なんですけど
but I've still got the upper hand.
Sh-Shoot! If he captures my rook...
（松永）し… しまった
角を打たれたら…
Glance.
（零）チラッて…
え？ 何？ 誘ってるの？
"Glance"? What?
Is he luring me in?!
Is he babbling?! Hiding his true intentions?! But his acting is bad!
三味… 三味線？
つーか 演技力低っ
Way too much
Th-This is painful.
辛い
ほんと何か マジで辛いんですが…
Way too much
This is seriously painful for some reason.
I've never felt like this.
Way too much
こんなの初めて
It'd be difficult to lose on purpose, even if I wanted to!
わざと負けようにも
それすら既に難しい
Way too much
E-Enough. Let's finish this.
も… もう終わりにしよう
Yes!
そうしよう
It kind of makes you worry.
（香子）心配だわ
だってほら あなたって優しいから
Seeing as you're such a nice guy.
I'm really sorry.
（零）ほんとすみません
Such a nice guy, such a nice guy, such a nice guy...
I'm grateful you said that about me, but I don't think I'm nice at all.
（零）
そこまで言っていただいといて
あれなんですけど—
僕 優しさとか
実は持ってないらしいです
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
I'm sorry! I'm from the pressure-free generation,
with no patience!
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
（零）すみません
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
こらえ性のない
ゆとり世代で
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Matsunaga, 7-dan, appears!
Fight
Escape
Strategy
Items
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
Player: Kiriyama
Choose a strategy
Take care of your life
Let's go attack
I'm really sorry!
もう ほんとすみません
Fifteen minutes later
（松永）うぐ… うぐぐ…
I...
lost...
けまし…
dammit!
Clatter
Shogi players must
never do this.
Clatter
Wh-What a bad attitude!
（零）た… 態度悪っ
What? What's going on?!
何だ？ それ何だよ
棋士人生 40年の重みは？
Where's the dignity of forty years of pro shogi?!
ていうか
人としてどうなの？ それ
I mean, even as a human being, what is this?!
Are you sure you want to go out this way?!
いんですか？ そんなんで
うわ〜ん！
At least make me respect you!
尊敬させてよ〜
（零）はっ　もういい
Enough.
Hurry! Let's hurry and go home!
早く… 早く帰ろう
I don't want to wait together for the elevator with him,
so I'll dash down the stairs!
エレベーター待ちとかで
一緒とか嫌だから
階段で ダダーッと…
Gasp
Apparently was thinking
the same thing
Trip
Ba-Bam
キャーッ！ 松永さん
Matsunaga!
くふふ…
あの 大丈夫ですか？
Um... are you okay?
大丈夫なものかっ
Do I look okay?
I nearly died!
死ぬとこだったんだぞ
Let's get you to a doctor. I'll go with you!
やっぱり医者に行きましょう
一緒に行きますから
Doctor? I don't like doctors!
えー 医者？ 医者は好かん
It was just a small trip.
転んだぐらいで
何が医者だ
これだから
最近の若い者(もん)は情けない
This is why you youngsters are so pathetic.
でも今 死ぬところだったって…
But you said you nearly died!
Shut up! Stop whining!
うるさいっ
ゴチャゴチャ言うな！
Go, already! Get lost!
もう行け！ 行ってくれ
I don't want to see your face—
わしは今 お前の顔は見たくな…
Grumble
Grumble Grumble Grumble Grumble Grumble
Treat me.
おごれ
Grumble Grumble Grumble Grumble Grumble
Treat me to soba! No, grilled eel!
おごれ！ そばだ！
いや うなぎだー！
What?!
えー？
今 もう行けって言いましたよね？
But you just told me to get lost!
だから どっちですか？
Which is it?!
（松永）
特上だ！ 金持ってんだろ？
こんちきしょう！
The deluxe meal! You've got the money, don't you?!
Distant Thunder (Part 2)
Cat Shogi Sing-along
Let's learn how to play shogi with cats!
You watch diagonally as far as the eye can see and advance with reckless abandon
You dish out powerful attacks, but your defenses are weak
That's the bishop in shogi!
Next up is the king!
You are the king, the most important part of the battle
You're the fighter that sits way in the back, and the game ends if you get captured
That's the king in shogi!
And that's shogi!
There are eight different types of pieces in shogi
Friend and enemy alike fight on a board of 81 squares
And now you know how to play shogi!
Distant Thunder (Part 3)
ホッ ホフ ホフ
Delicious!
うまい　この香り
さすが天下の「宮乃川(みやのかわ)」さんじゃ〜
This aroma! The famous Mr. Miyanogawa does not disappoint!
(2-layer deluxe meal)
It's hot and tender to the core!
芯まで熱々のトロトロじゃ〜
(Standard meal on bamboo)
What is it, kid? Your first time eating eel?
何じゃ 坊主
うなぎは初めてか？
うまいだろ？
Delicious, right?
If you wanna be first-class,
you gotta start by eating first-class food.
やはり 一流になるためには
一流のものを食わにゃ始まらんぞ
Am I right?
どうよ おう？
Heheh
Chew
Well, I am paying for this.
ま　僕のおごりですけどね
Chew
Oh, jeez.
（松永）
あ〜 嫌だ 嫌だ　堅いなぁ〜
Don't be so stiff.
Not a single drop of emotion.
情緒もへったくれもない
You're ruining the taste of my beer! Grr.
ビールがまずくなるわ
プン プン
ハア〜
Well, Kouda is your foster father.
ま あの幸田が育ての親じゃな
He was also a prize pupil and really good at shogi, but he had no personality whatsoever.
あれも ほんと優等生で
ただ強いだけの
面白みのないやつじゃった
Come to think of it, he's got that daughter too. A real "darling."
あ〜 そういや
娘もまた 憎たらしいやつだったな
Strong-willed, with a face as beautiful as the devil.
気が強くて 鬼のように
きれいな顔しとったが
But she's pretty scary.
じゃが あれは おっかないぞ
When she becomes an adult, just you wait.
大人になったら あれだ
毒婦ってやつになるな
She'll become a poisonous woman.
Living under a roof with that kind of person, I bet you got tormented by her.
お前も あんなんが
同じ屋根の下にいて
相当いたぶられたんじゃないか？
But, y'know, all women are scary.
でも ま
女はみんな怖いもんだがな
You should meet my wife, sheesh...
うちのかあちゃんなんて
そりゃあもう…
Splish
（松永）おっと
（零）そんなにも…？
Splash
Shudder
Oops!
Splash
Shudder
That scary?!
Splash
Shudder
Bad topic. It's makin' the booze go bad.
いけね 酒がまずくならぁ
そうだ すみません
日本酒… 日本酒のお品書きを
I know. Excuse me!
Sake! The sake menu, please!
おお“会津(あいず)の魂”があるじゃないか
Fukushima
Soul of Aizu
They've got Soul of Aizu!
Do you know about Soul of Aizu?
知っとるか？ 会津の魂
It's sake from my hometown, Aizu.
わしのふるさと 会津の酒じゃ
ん〜 いい香りじゃ
It smells great.
東京の者(もん)は
福島の人間のことを
Tokyoites say people from Fukushima are "stubborn" and "too serious."
頑固だ 真面目すぎだなどと
言いよるが
But we're aware of our surroundings and emphasize etiquette.
礼節を重んじ 常に周囲を気遣う
They're clueless about the soul of the true Fukushima!
真の福島の魂を 全く分かっとらん
Hmph
Let's go back to the year 1643.
Matsunaga
Shouichi
遡れば1643年
３代将軍 徳川(とくがわ)家光(いえみつ)より
The third Tokugawa shogun, Iemitsu,
Matsunaga
Shouichi
recognized a minor feudal lord with just 30,000 koku for his shrewdness and stern honesty.
たった３万石の 小さな
藩主だったにもかかわらず
He was granted an extremely generous 230,000 koku and became the first-generation feudal lord of Aizu.
その辣腕(らつわん)と
謹厳実直さを認められ
23万石という
大変な引き立てを賜り
Hoshina Masayuki
That was Hoshina Masayuki.
初代会津藩主となった保科(ほしな)正之(まさゆき)
He was a truly wise ruler!
このお方が いかに名君であったか
Masayuki was not only an administrator, but was made the adjunct to the fourth Tokugawa shogun, Ietsuna.
Matsunaga
Shouichi
正之は 藩政のみならず
４代将軍
家綱(いえつな)の補佐役をもまかされ
As the center of the shogunate administration, he set forth a number of policies.
幕政においても 中枢として
ビシビシと
政策を打ち出していったのじゃぞ
In order to provide the residents of Edo with drinking water,
Matsunaga
Shouichi
Tamagawa
Water Supply
江戸(えど)の人々の飲料水確保のため
玉川(たまがわ)上水の河川工事を行い
he created the Tamagawa water supply river works.
To prevent neighboring dwellings from burning in a fire,
Matsunaga
Shouichi
Ueno
Main Streets
火事の際
隣家への類焼を防ぐため
主要な大通りの幅を ６間から
10間に広げ 火よけ地とし
he widened streets from six to ten ken,
and established main streets in Ueno as a firebreak.
上野に広小路を設置
When a plan to rebuild the tower of the burnt down Edo Castle came up, he rejected it.
焼け落ちた江戸城の
天守閣の再建案が出た折は
"Peace reigns in the land, so it's unnecessary. No need to waste expenditures!"
天下太平の
今の世の中には必要ない
無駄な出費は不要と却下
く〜 何たる英断　何たる男気
How decisive! How manly!
He's the pride of Aizu!
まさに会津の誇り
And do you know the pension system?
それに知っとるか？ 年金制度
これも 大本は
正之と言われとるのだ
It's said Masayuki devised that too.
To prepare for a famine,
正之は 飢きんに備え
民衆のために
米を蔵に貯める社倉法を定め
he laid down a law stating that rice be stored in granaries as well as distributed for free to people aged 90 or older,
また 90歳以上の老人には
身分を問わず
whatever their social status.
無料で米を配布するという
It's said that our pension system today is based on that.
今の日本の年金制度の
元を作ったともいわれておるのじゃ
この福祉に重きを置いた正之の
清く正しく慈悲あふるる精神が
Masayuki, who stressed welfare of the people, had a spirit flowing with genuine benevolence
that even now supports the sincere hearts of Fukushima Prefecture citizens today!
いかに今日の福島県民の
心根の実直さを支えておるか
Do you get it, young'un?
分かるか？ 若造
Now let's leap forward 250 years, to the Boshin War.
そして話は 250年飛んで
いよいよ 戊辰(ぼしん)戦争へと…
Y-You're continuing?
（零）ま… まだ続くんですか？
But before that, I'll have another Soul of Aizu!
その前に
ちょいと会津の魂 おかわり〜
プハッ
うまいっ
Delicious!
So what was I saying?
で〜 何 話しとったっけ？
Oh, right. My grandson's name is Kousuke, and boy is he a handful...
あ〜 そうそう
うちの孫 コウスケってんだけど…
Wait a second!
（零）ちょっと待って
Snap
What happened to the Boshin War?
戊辰戦争は？
Snap
Still a child, so not accustomed to the behaviors of a drunk
What happened to the talk about the souls of people from Fukushima?
福島県人の魂の話は
どうなったの？
Thank you.
Eel Miyanogawa
（店員）ありがとうございました〜
That legendary thing (souvenir)
（松永）よーし
All right, let's go to the next place!
That legendary thing (souvenir)
次 行っちゃうぞ
Wobble
He's a drunk.
（零）酔っ払いだ
He's the exact image of a drunk.
絵に描いたような酔っ払いだ
Huh?
えっ？
今 もう１軒って言いました？
Did you just say "another place"?!
But I'm going home!
僕 もう帰りますよ？
もう お金無いし
Besides, I'm out of money!
バカも〜ん
勝ったやつが先に帰るとは何事だ
Idiot! What kind of winner says "I'm going home" first?
次は わしのおごりだ
I'll pay for the next one.
I know just the place!
いいとこ連れてってやる
ハア
Stagger
Limp
Crack
（松永）えっ うおお
（零）危なっ！
Careful!
Please watch where you walk!
ほら しっかり足元 見てください
すまん すまん　ハハ
Sorry, sorry.
あ…
どうも このごろ酒が足にきてなぁ
Seems the booze goes straight to my legs these days.
（零）細い腕
His arm is so thin.
（零）40年
駒だけをつかんで生きてきた腕
The arm of a man who's grasped nothing but shogi pieces for forty years.
（香子）松永さん
ついに引退するらしいわよ
I hear Matsunaga will finally retire.
I had a feeling I couldn't win.
勝てる気がせんかった
Huh?
I had a feeling I wouldn't be able to win at all.
ほんの髪の毛ひと筋も
勝てる気がせんかった
会館に着くまでは
All I thought about on the way to the shogi hall was "How can I look cool losing?"
どうやって かっこよく
負けるかばっかり考えていた
You probably didn't know me, but I know a lot about you.
お前は
わしを知らんかったろうが
わしは
お前のことをよく知っとった
何せ史上たった５人目の
中学生プロだ
After all, you're only the fifth
junior high student to turn pro.
I've held fast to the shogi board for forty years without any records to show for it,
40年 盤にしがみついても
何の記録も
残せんかったわしには
ただ ただ 悔しく
まぶしい存在だった
so to me, your existence was
something bright and frustrating.
わしには お前が
I could only think of you as the Grim Reaper,
come to close the curtain on my life as a shogi player.
わしの将棋人生に
幕を引きに来た—
死神のようにしか思えんかった
I was frightened of you,
ただ ただ 恐ろしく
また そう思う己が情けなかった
and then I was disgusted with myself for feeling that way.
But when I saw you sitting up straight in the match room,
しかし あの対局室で
正座するお前を見た瞬間 思った
I had a thought.
"Such a young, beautiful Grim Reaper."
なんと若く美しい
死神なのであろうかと
If you would.
（零）お願いします
（松永）幕を引く相手としては
これ以上のものはないと思った
If someone was going to close the curtain, I couldn't ask for anyone better.
せめて正々堂々戦って 散ろうと…
I thought I would at least fight fair and square once more before fading away.
なのに… それなのに…
And yet, in spite of that...
わしの中身が暴れだしたんじゃ
something inside of me began to struggle.
It screamed out, "I don't want to die!"
死にたくないと
最後に用意された花道の上を
Here I was at the end of my long career,
muddying my legacy, struggling pathetically,
泥まみれでみっともなく
あがきまわりながらも
and one thought welled up from within.
どうしようもなく
込み上げてきたのは
負けたくない
"I don't want to lose."
"Even still, I don't want to lose."
それでも
わしは負けたくないという
That was my crazed line of thought.
狂おしいばかりの気持ちじゃった
（零）松永さん
Matsunaga.
Do you like shogi?
将棋好きですか？
知らん
I don't know.
How the hell would I know?
知るもんか
When I won, I'd be so happy that I'd want to shout with joy.
（松永）勝ったときは
叫び出すほどうれしくて
When I lost, it was agonizing,
like somebody had trampled my innards with muddy boots.
負ければ 内臓を泥靴で
踏みにじられるように苦しくて
I'd feel tormented from everyone saying that I didn't deserve to be alive.
世界中に 生きる価値無しと
言われたような
気持ちに さいなまれた
Yet...
なのに…
それなのに 辞められなかった
And yet, I couldn't quit.
How can I...
この気持ちを…
possibly express this feeling in words?!
そんな言葉なんぞで
言い表せるものか！
Hello?
零　今どこ？
Rei? Where are you?
I figured you'd be depressed,
so I thought I could cheer you up.
へこんでいると思ったから
慰めてあげようかと思って
I heard.
聞いたわ　今日勝ったんでしょ？
You won, right?
It's a match. One of you has to lose.
しかたないわよ 勝負ですもの
It's not your fault.
あなたのせいじゃないわ
So...
（香子）だから…
（零）辞めないよ 松永さん
Matsunaga isn't going to quit.
続けるって 将棋
He's going to keep playing shogi.
What? What does that mean?
何？ それ
どういうこと？
Rei. Rei?
零？　零？
（零）さあ 行きますよ
Well, let's go.
Right.
お… おう
Come on. Stand up.
（零）立って しっかり
Yeah.
（松永）おう
Hey.
（松永）なあ お前からも
女房と娘 説得してくれんか？
Would you help me convince my wife and daughter?
That I've decided not to retire after all.
引退をしないと決めたことを
皆さん 心配してるんですね
They must be worried about you.
Shogi players do need physical strength.
棋士は 体力がいりますものね
辞めたくないんじゃ
I don't want to quit.
辞めたら わしは…
If I do quit...
I can't act like a big deal at home anymore!
家で
威張れなくなってしまう！
（零）うぐっ
Sigh
All this time, I've never helped with chores, saying I needed to focus on shogi.
今まで将棋のためだと言って
家では一切 何もしてこんかった
これで辞めたら
If I quit now, I know exactly how my family will take their revenge!
家族から どんな仕返しがあるか
分かったもんじゃない
What?! That's the reason?!
（零）
おい こら　そんな理由でかよ！
My blood runs cold just thinking about it!
考えただけでも身が凍るわ
（松永の妻）フフフ
さぁ これからは 家事は分担よ
Hahaha
From now on, you're doing your share of the housework.
I can't wait to train you!
仕込みがいがあるわ〜
（松永の娘）
ホッホホホ　お父さん
Heehee
Hahaha
Dad, give Kou a bath!
コウちゃんを
お風呂に入れて〜
Hahaha
（コウスケ）バブー
Heehee
Gaga
Hahaha
The horror!
恐ろしい　皿洗ったり
孫を洗ったりさせられる
They'll make me wash dishes,
and they'll make me wash my grandson too!
Wash them! Both! Don't wait until you retire!
洗おうよ　そこは洗っとこうよ
引退しなくても
I don't wanna!
（松永）嫌じゃ〜
（零）
“嫌じゃ”じゃなくて
家族は助け合うものなんです！
Don't complain!
Family members should help each other!
You want me to teach you how to do chores?!
何なら
僕 教えましょうか？ 家事
（松永）
嫌じゃ 嫌じゃ 嫌じゃ〜
I don't wanna! I don't wanna! I don't wanna!
何と言われようとも
絶対に嫌じゃ〜
No matter what anyone says, I definitely don't wanna!
Distant Thunder (Part 3)
Like a resplendent meteor shower
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Next Episode Preview
Episode 10
When did it start?
（零）いつごろからだろう
When did Christmas
become painful for me?
クリスマスを
苦しいと思うようになったのは
Hey, Dad, can we open it now?
（香子）ねえ お父さん
もう開けていい？
（幸田(こうだ)歩(あゆむ)）
お〜 ゲームボムだ
A Game Bomb!
What do you think, Rei?
（幸田(こうだ)柾近(まさちか)）どうだ？ 零
I'm happy with these.
（零）
すっごくうれしいです
Which would be more fitting
as a final Christmas memory?
（香子）
最後のクリスマスの思い出に
ぴったりなのは どっちかしら
Illustration: Oshikiri Rensuke
３月のライオン
次回を見ないとか—
You won't watch the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion"?
Excuse me?
何それ？ あり得ない
That's impossible.